Finding Aid of the AT & T Records of the Olympic Torch Relay LSC.1450
UCLA Library Special Collections
AT & T Records of the Olympic Torch Relay
1983-1984
UCLA Library Special Collections
American Telephone and Telegraph Company
LSC.1450
27 Linear Feet (54 boxes)
The 1984 Olympic torch relay, sponsored and documented by AT & T, began in New York City on May 8, 1984 and ended in the Los Angeles Coliseum on July 28, 1984 at the opening of the 1984 Summer Olympic Games. The collection consists of a torch, motion picture film scripts, videotapes, press releases, maps, clothing, correspondence, and files regarding the relay.
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Advance notice required for access.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of American Telephone and Telegraph Company, 1988.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303373606533
Biography
The 1984 Olympic torch relay, sponsored and documented by AT & T, began in New York City on May 8, 1984 and ended in the Los Angeles Coliseum on July 28, 1984 at the opening of the 1984 Summer Olympic Games; the flame traveled over 9,000 miles during an eighty-two day journey, and an estimated 30 million viewers lined the route; Rafer Johnson lit the cauldron upon the flame's arrival at the Coliseum.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of a torch, motion picture film scripts, videotapes, press releases, maps, clothing, correspondence, and files regarding Olympic torch relay for the 1984 Summer Olympic Games in Los Angeles. Includes approximately 5,000 color transparencies, several hundred black and white photographs, and a copy of Mickey Herscowitz's book, One with the flame. Files from Telephone Pioneers of America related to the relay route are in the collection. Also includes 53 hours of 16mm film footage used to produce videos of relay.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
One with the flame files.
Videotapes.
Operations.
Clippings.
Photographs, slides, and contact sheets.
Carry the fire files.
Objects for display.
Films.
Related Material
Los Angeles Olympic Organizing Committee Records (Collection 1403). Available at Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Olympic torch relay -- United States -- Archives.; American Telephone and Telegraph Company--Archives.; Telephone Pioneers of America.
- One With the Flame Files
  - Sponsors. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Names of contacts with addresses and phone numbers.
  - Schedules. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Several versions of relay schedules - dates, cities and towns listed.
  - AT & T contacts. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Names and phone numbers.
  - Reader's Digest article. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Article sent to R. Wilbins from mother of youngest torch bearer.
  - Messenger's videotape script. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Transcript of "Carry the Fire," video produced by AT&T.
  - Caravan briefing book. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Describing the operations of the relay.
  - Olympics 1984 - AT&T - technology (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Article on the temporary communications network assembly by AT&T at the sites of the 1984 Olympics.
  - Politicians. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Statements, quotes, proclamations by governors, mayors, senators, representatives, etc.
  - AT&T medical staff. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Names of AT&T doctors schedules to accompany the relay.
  - AT&T cadre runners. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    List.
  - Activities and milestones. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    PERT chart for relay planning by AT&T managers.
  - Ham radio. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Background use of ham radio communication on the relay.
  - AT&T internal. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Articles written by AT&T writers for company publications.
  - Interviews: Boehmer, Putnam, Washburn. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Interview with Mickey Hershowitz.
  - Pioneers. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Background on Telephone Pioneer involvement: statements, quotes, press releases, etc. and Pioneer executives correspondence.
  - Pioneer region. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Names, addresses, phone numbers.
  - Pioneer press clippings. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Compiled by Telephone Pioneers of America.
  - News clippings summaries. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Excerpts of media coverage of the relay.
  - Press releases. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Issued by AT&T.
  - Logistics, [2 folders] (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    Background on logistics planning and execution - interviews with key persons - clippings, correspondence, etc.
  - Song lyrics, 1984. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Lyrics to past Olympics songs and 1984, lyrics to "Carry the fire."
  - Mickey Hershowitz. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Articles on MLH, author of "One with the flame."
  - AT&T media clippings. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Compiled and summarized by AT&T.
  - Burson-Marstellar. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Background information on public relations firm hired by AT&T to handle media and miscellaneous function of relay.
  - Interviews. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Highlighted quotes from persons interviewed.
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Notes and clippings.
  - Copy of the book One With the Flame. (Box 35, Folder 1)
- Videotapes
  - Videotape overview of the AT&T Olympic Torch Relay archive. (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Corporate sponsorship of the Olympics, October 22, 1984, Saturday 10:30p.m. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Wall Street Journal report - WPIC-TV.
  - Electronic media: representative coverage, May 7-June 12.; 27:00 minutes. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Carry the fire,", November 20, 1985.; 3:50. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    AT&T.
  - "In the best American Spirit,", November 1984.; 16:00. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Burson-Marsteller.
  - Connections, May 4, 1984.; :30. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Young and Rubicam.
  - Torch run media briefing - Crossroads - "In the best American spirit.", 10:13, AT&T - 12:30. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Charles Kurault - CBS - AT&T.
  - Olympic torch relay, September 6, 1983. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Burson-Marstellar.
  - Olympic torch, October 28, 1983. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Olympic torch relay, May 18, 1984. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Olympic torch relay, feed 9, July 17, 1984. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Olympic countdown, November 1, 1979.; 10:00. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The struggle and the triumph, February 2, 1983.; 11:00. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Kipony Productions and the U.S. Olympic Committee.
  - Celebrate the spirit., 4:00. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Radio TV Reports, Incorporated. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Commercials of official sponsors (several reports on one videotape).
  - Transcripts of film footage photographed by AT&T. (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Operations
  - Road maps., [2 folders] (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    For initial planning of the relay route.
  - Road maps., [4 folders] (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Amerite.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Bell South.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Bell Labs.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    AT&T-C.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    WECO.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    U.S. West.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Pacific Telephone.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    NYNAX.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Bell Atlantic.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 11, Folder 3)
    AT&T International.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Southwestern Bell.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    CSO.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Sandia.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 11, Folder 7)
    SNET.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Teletype.
  - Original cadre applications. (Box 11, Folder 9)
    TRNST.
  - GMC truck. (Box 22, Folder 1)
    Plans, correspondence and miscellaneous material on special relay trucks and vans.
  - McDonalds. (Box 22, Folder 2)
    Sub-sponsor proposal.
  - National Severe Storm Warning Center. (Box 22, Folder 3)
    Weather report agreement.
  - United Airlines. (Box 22, Folder 4)
    Flight reservations plans for relay personnel.
  - LAOOC torch operating plan. (Box 22, Folder 5)
    1983 plans.
  - Security. (Box 22, Folder 6)
    Plans, correspondence with J. Mattman Security.
  - Converse. (Box 22, Folder 7)
    Correspondence and procedures.
  - ARA. (Box 22, Folder 8)
    Plans, correspondence, blueprints, c/c/w Dining car and relay food positioning.
  - Logistics section. (Box 22, Folder 10)
    Initial draft of operations plan section.
  - Burson-Marsteller. (Box 22, Folder 11)
    Correspondence.
  - Levi. (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Levi-Security / Pioneer. (Box 23, Folder 2)
    Clothing plans forms.
  - Cadre selection. (Box 23, Folder 3)
    Cadre planning tasks and operation plan.
  - Scheduling Pert. (Box 23, Folder 4)
    Activities/Milestone schedule.
  - Olympic business plan., (binder) (Box 24, Folder 1)
    AT&T plan for sponsorship of torch relay.
  - America. (Box 24, Folder 2)
    Personal scrapbook of AT&T relay managers.
  - 4/5 Vugraphs to LAOOC, April 5, 1983. (Box 24, Folder 3)
    AT&T presentation to LAOOC.
  - Computer. (Box 24, Folder 4)
    Computer and data support for Torch Relay Management.
  - Communication. (Box 24, Folder 5)
    Radio communication for relay.
  - Address list. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Addresses and phone numbers of persons involved with the relay.
  - Press kits. (Box 25, Folder 2)
    AT&T media kits for the relay.
  - Pioneer. (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Caravan personnel. (Box 25, Folder 4)
    Names of persons on official Torch Relay Caravan.
  - Block schedule. (Box 25, Folder 5)
    Daily itineraries for the relay.
  - Bill Higgins. (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Kate Washburn. (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - FAX copies. (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Cathy Basinski. (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Dick Boehner. (Box 26, Folder 5)
    Correspondence and miscellaneous files.
  - Lou Putnam. (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - AT&T sponsorship overview. (Box 27, Folder 2)
    Miscellaneous presentation.
  - Torch run liability. (Box 27, Folder 3)
    AT&T insurance and liability for the torch relay.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence., [flat box] (Box 28, Folder 1)
    "Ditto."
  - Corporate cup, 1983. (Box 28, Folder 2)
    AT&T's participation in 1983.
  - Olympic torch relay planning document. (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Olympic torch relay operations handbook. (Box 31, Folder 10)
    Burson-Marsteller handbook for Pioneers.
  - Letters to region and state coordinators and conference call minutes. (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - Moving caravan briefing book. (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Telephone Pioneers of America. (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Telephone Pioneers of America. (Box 32, Folder 2)
    Involvement in the 1984 Olympic torch run.
  - Pre-relay Olympic Torch Relay slides and talk. (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Publicity - Burson-Marsteller P.R. (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - First draft of Pioneer organization and tasks for Olympic Torch Relay Project. (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Sale of memorabilia. (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Olympic Torch Relay Region 2 - Summary / Newsclips Pioneers. (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Telephone Pioneers of America correspondence and reminiscences. (Box 32, Folder 8)
- Clippings
  - Media clippings, [22 f] (Box 4, Folder 12-16)
- Photographs
  - Photographs - color slides., [12 f] (Box 5, Folder 17-19)
  - Photographs - color slides. (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs., Black and white contact sheets. (Box 20, Folder 3)
    Photos taken of the relay.
    Prints available through Associated Press/Wide World Photo in New York.
  - Photographs., Black and white contact sheets [4 f]. (Box 21)
- "Carry the Fire" Files
  - PBS airings of "Carry the fire." (Box 29, Folder 1)
    Airdates, correspondence, reaction.
  - Order forms and information sheets. (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - USIA. (Box 29, Folder 3)
    Distribution via satellite feed USIA.
  - Torch article. (Box 29, Folder 4)
    Background article on the making of "Carry the fire."
  - Torch summary. (Box 29, Folder 5)
    Synopsis and other summary materials re "Carry the fire."
  - Academy Awards. (Box 29, Folder 6)
    Festivals entered and won.
  - News and fact sheets. (Box 29, Folder 7)
    Includes letter to director of UCLA Film Archives re possibility of depositing the film - promotional material related to Chandler Pavilion premiere.
  - Rick Wilbin. (Box 29, Folder 8)
    "One with the flame."
  - Transcript. (Box 29, Folder 9)
    Finished film (continuity).
  - Torch route cities list. (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Credits. (Box 29, Folder 11)
    Production credits.
  - Copyright. (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Edit down. (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Gift copies. (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Los Angeles premiere. (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - To discuss with Mary Lou. (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Sound logs. (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Greece. (Box 30, Folder 7)
    Filming arrangements.
  - PBS 28:30. (Box 30, Folder 8)
    30 second/60 second promotional.
  - Speaking engagement - Denver Pioneers, April 12, 1985. (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Narration - Frank Converse paperwork. (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Torch book sets. (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - Joan Stocker - Customer Advisory Board, May 9. (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - Promotion and distribution of "Carry the fire." (Box 30, Folder 13)
  - "Carry the fire" use guide. (Box 30, Folder 14)
  - News clippings. (Box 30, Folder 15)
  - Tobias show, May. (Box 30, Folder 16)
  - Proposed script: "In the best American way." (Box 30, Folder 17)
  - Narration. (Box 30, Folder 18)
  - Olympic torch run. (Box 30, Folder 19)
    5 minute promotional.
  - Torch relay stock footage requests. (Box 30, Folder 20)
  - C-Cam tape for Bill Higgins. (Box 30, Folder 22)
  - Original - "Carry the fire." (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Master script. (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Original short script. (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Film schedule. (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Treatment, original - Olympic torch run. (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Master script "In the best American spirit." (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Torch releases and news stories. (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Film festivals. (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Children's letters and artwork inspired by "Carry the Fire." (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - 2 films., Flat box. (Box 33, Folder 1)
    Projection and protection 16 mm film prints of "Carry the Fire."
- Objects for Display
  - Objects for display. (Box 36)
    Contains AT&T Press Kits, "Sam the Olympic Eagle" balloon, sample uniform, Olympic torch operating instructions.
- Films
  - Sacramento, California. (Box 38)
  - Sacramento - San Francisco - Davis, California. (Box 38)
  - San Francisco (Golden Gate) - North Beach - E. Oakland, California. (Box 38)
  - Monterey - Salinas Valley - San Ardo, California. (Box 38)
  - Carmel - San Miguel, California. (Box 38)
  - Pismo Beach, California. (Box 38)
  - Santa Maria, California. (Box 38)
  - Santa Barbara, California. (Box 38)
  - Santa Barbara - Oxnard, California. (Box 39)
  - Oxnard, California. (Box 39)
  - Los Angeles, California. (Box 39)
  - Hollywood, California. (Box 39)
  - Downtown Los Angeles - Northridge, California. (Box 39)
  - New York City, New York - Connecticut. (Box 39)
  - New York City, New York. (Box 39)
  - Boston, Massachusetts. (Box 39)
  - Boston, Massachusetts - Bedminster, New Jersey. (Box 40)
  - Hartford, Connecticut. (Box 40)
  - Woodbury - Newtown, Connecticut - Connecticut / New York border - West Point, New York. (Box 40)
  - Annapolis, Maryland. (Box 40)
  - West Point, New York. (Box 40)
  - Washington, D.C. (Box 40)
  - Far Hills, New Jersey - North Carolina. (Box 40)
  - Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. (Box 40)
  - Pittsburgh - Akron, Pennsylvania. (Box 40)
  - Cleveland, Ohio. (Box 40)
  - Dinasaur Company - Roosevelt, Utah. (Box 41)
  - Utah: Roosevelt - Route 40. (Box 41)
  - Unknown location. (Box 41)
  - Roosevelt - Current Creek - Salt Lake City, Utah. (Box 41)
  - Unknown location. (Box 41)
  - Sacramento - San Francisco - Foster City, California. (Box 41)
  - Sacramento, California. (Box 41)
  - San Francisco - Sacramento, California (Aerials). (Box 41)
  - Monterey, California. (Box 41)
  - Pismo Beach, California. (Box 41)
  - St. Lucas - San Ardo - Bradley - San Miguel, California. (Box 42)
  - Unknown location. (Box 42)
  - Santa Barbara, California (Trip director's car). (Box 42)
  - Pismo Beach - Oxnard - outside Los Angeles, California. (Box 42)
  - Los Angeles - Beverly Hills - Santa Monica, California. (Box 42)
  - Texas - "Torch Run" - Sync reel 3. (Box 42)
  - Texas - "Torch Run" - Sync reel 1. (Box 42)
  - "Torch Run" - "Coachwork" - Sync reel 1A. (Box 42)
  - "Coachwork" - Sync reel 6A. (Box 42)
  - Simulation II - "Olympic Torch Relay." (Box 42)
  - "Torch Run" - Sync reel 7 - New York. (Box 43)
  - Los Angeles, California (final day). (Box 43)
  - New York City. (Box 43)
  - Unknown location. (Box 43)
  - Unknown location. (Box 43)
  - Birmingham, Alabama. (Box 43)
  - Gatlinburg, Tennessee. (Box 43)
  - Vermillion, Ohio. (Box 43)
  - Vermillion, Ohio - Detroit. (Box 43)
  - "Olympic Torch Relay." (Box 44)
  - "Olympic Relay." (Box 44)
  - "Olympic Torch Run." (Box 45)
  - "Torch Run" - "Coachworks." (Box 45)
  - Simulation w/pix w/trk - - Sync reel P4., March 17, 1984 (Box 46)
  - Simulation "Torch Run" - - Sync reel 1., March 17, 1984 (Box 46)
  - Albuquerque, New Mexico. (Box 47)
  - "Slo mo runner." (Box 47)
  - Wenatche, Washington. (Box 47)
  - Los Angeles opening ceremonies. (Box 47)
  - Indianapolis (blimp). (Box 47)
  - New York City. (Box 47)
  - Washington, D.C. (Box 47)
  - New York City. (Box 47)
  - Washington, D.C. (Box 47)
  - Albuquerque, New Mexico. (Box 47)
  - Albuquerque, New Mexico. (Box 48)
  - Albuquerque - Sante Fe, New Mexico. (Box 48)
  - Colorado. (Box 48)
  - Colorado (food car). (Box 48)
  - Colorado scenes. (Box 48)
  - Denver, Colorado. (Box 48)
  - Colorado - Utah. (Box 48)
  - Denver, Colorado. (Box 48)
  - Golden, Colorado. (Box 48)
  - Colorado (torch 27). (Box 48)
  - Georgia. (Box 49)
  - Birmingham, Alabama. (Box 49)
  - Colorado Springs, Colorado. (Box 49)
  - Denver - Colorado Springs, Colorado. (Box 49)
  - Denver, Colorado. (Box 49)
  - Golden, Colorado. (Box 49)
  - Golden - Idaho Springs, Colorado. (Box 49)
  - Golden, Colorado. (Box 49)
  - Colorado - Rockies - Continental Divide. (Box 49)
  - Craig County, Colorado. (Box 49)
  - Interview with Wally McGuire. (Box 50)
  - EMS - Torch 7. (Box 50)
  - Craig County, Colorado. (Box 50)
  - Route 40 - Dinasaur County, Colorado. (Box 50)
  - Denver: Food preparation. (Box 50)
  - Colorado (interview). (Box 50)
  - Craig County, Colorado. (Box 50)
  - Colorado / Utah border. (Box 50)
  - Colorado - Utah. (Box 50)
  - Salt Lake City, Utah. (Box 51)
  - Mountain Home, Idaho. (Box 51)
  - Mountain Home - Boise, Idaho. (Box 51)
  - Kansas - Washington - Idaho. (Box 51)
  - Pendelton, Oregon. (Box 51)
  - Winache, Washington (interview). (Box 51)
  - Winanche, Washington. (Box 51)
  - Wenatchee, Washington. (Box 51)
  - Seattle, Washington. (Box 51)
  - Pasadena, California. (Box 51)
  - Corona - East Los Angeles, California. (Box 52)
  - Interview with Mrs. Salisbury. (Box 52)
  - Flatbed - Disneyland, California. (Box 52)
  - La Jolla - San Diego, California. (Box 52)
  - Opening ceremonies. (Box 52)
  - Unknown location. (Box 52)
  - Runner on beach (California). (Box 52)
  - Van Nuys - Burbank - Pasadena, California. (Box 52)
  - Los Angeles, Culver City, California. (Box 52)
  - Manhattan Beach - Culver City, California - Interview with Dick Sargeant. (Box 52)
  - Los Angeles, California. (Box 53)
  - Opening ceremonies. (Box 53)
  - Chicago, Illinois. (Box 53)
  - Hammond, Indiana. (Box 53)
  - Sycamore, Illinois. (Box 53)
  - Kentucky. (Box 53)
  - Frankfurt - Berea, Kentucky. (Box 53)
  - Berea, Kentucky. (Box 53)
  - Berea, Kentucky. (Box 53)
  - Arrival at stadium. (Box 54)
  - Berea, Kentucky - Sugarland - Gatlinburg, Tennessee (Smokies). (Box 54)
  - Dahlonega, Georgia - Sugarland, Tennessee. (Box 54)
  - Atlanta - Dahlonega, Georgia. (Box 54)
  - Atlanta - Dahlonega, Georgia. (Box 54)
  - Dahlonega, Georgia. (Box 54)
  - Dahlonega, Georgia. (Box 54)
  - Atlanta, Georgia. (Box 54)
  - Atlanta - Oxford - Lincoln - Riverside - Birmingham. (Box 54)
  - Alabama. (Box 54)